Hello everyone. Um I am one of the last
speakers after me is Jeopardy and then
closing ceremonies and then lightning
talks. Yes. Okay. You been having a good
freaknic
winding down. Okay. Good. Good. All
right. So, Cryptos um this is an
exciting topic right now because it is
currently on auction. The fourth
unsolved part is on an online auction
which started a few weeks ago and wraps
up on November 20th. So, every single
day I'm watching the the counter tick
up. We'll see what it is when I get to
that part of the talk. All right. So, um
this is a sculpture at CIA. Sound okay?
Yeah. Okay. Uh this was uh installed a
few decades ago. The CIA on the right we
have the original headquarters building
and when they wanted their new
headquarters building on the left they
uh were sort of required to have some
art to go around the building and one of
the things that they requested they
formed a committee that formed a
committee that formed a committee and
they I'm not I'm not making that up. Uh
they decided to ask Jim Samborn who'd
already been doing art around the
Washington DC area and he decided uh
after doing some more research to do a
sculpture that had this uh theme of
things that are hidden. So he called it
cryptos which is Greek for the word
hidden. Uh I got a chance to see it.
These are rubbings that I did of it.
Each one is on a piece of paper a
standard 8 1/2 by 11. sort of gives you
an idea of the size of the sculpture. It
has about 2,000 characters that are
carved through it. And this is the
dedication in 1988. And there is Jim
Sanborn handing an envelope to the
director of the CIA at the time, William
Webster. We think we know what is in the
envelope. Um, but we're not sure. It was
It might have been the answer to
Kryptos. It might not. But he put
something in that envelope and it was
sealed and he asked William Webster at
the time, uh, can you keep a secret? And
William Webster said, "My lips are
sealed as is the envelope." So, Jim
Samborn, born in 1945, Washington DC,
studied at Oxford, uh has done a ton of
travel and um has a degree in social
anthropology for what that's worth, and
a master's degree in sculpture. And I
started making a list of all of his
works. So, this I'll tell you a little
bit of the story. I was at a convention
in Atlanta called Dragon Con. Anybody
here been to Dragon Con? A couple
people. So, it's a big fan convention.
Uh, brings in what, 60,000 people, takes
over downtown Atlanta. Uh, and um, I
have been asked to speak at the
convention on my job at the time, which
was making computer games. And we I was
speaking in the electronic frontiers
track. And at the end of the day, you
get together with the other speakers.
And some of the speakers at the time
were people from Nashville who had been
involved with creating this convention
called Freaknik. Freaknick 3 at the
time. And at the end of the day, you get
together, you have a drink, and they
told me about this code that had been
released at Freaknik 3, and no one had
cracked it yet. Had cracked it yet. So,
they were handing out code on a sheet of
paper saying if you can solve this
challenge, you get a free trip to a
hacker con, free drinks, free t-shirts,
all that. So, I picked it up with all
the stuff you get. This was in what, 23
years ago, so late '9s. And I took a
look at it and I was home one weekend. I
was kind of frustrated because I wanted
to go to Defcon, but I couldn't cuz I
was sick with the flu at the time. And I
took a look at the code and I got
obsessed with cracking this code. And my
friends sometimes they like send me a
text message saying, "Hey, do you want
to go out to a movie out?" Don't talk to
me unless you want to talk about the
code. And um it took me 10 days, but I
cracked it and felt like longer, but I
cracked it. And then I went around
cracking a bunch of other codes in the
hacker scene. uh so many that have
actually been banned from competition.
Like when the Atlanticon they had their
code was on a sheet of paper and at the
bottom of the paper it said past puzzle
solvers are ineligible with solving the
Atlanticon puzzle. Give someone else a
chance. Yanka. So So I cracked that one
too. And um then uh September 11th
happened and I was as enraged as
everyone else and I called up the local
FBI and I said, "Hey, can I help with
the war on terrorism?" And they said,
"No." And um I kept calling them up and
eventually they asked me, "What is it
that you know about?" And I said, "Well,
I've been cracking all these codes in
the hacker scene and I know about binary
and PGP and Neo encoding and
steanography and all this stuff." And
one of them said, "hm, steganography,
we've been hearing rumors that al-Qaeda
was using steganography as a way of
planning the September 11th attacks."
And you know, we know that there's big
brains in Washington DC that know about
this stuff, but we're here in St. Louis,
which is where I lived at the time, and
uh cryptography isn't really our
mission. Uh maybe you could come in and
put together a talk about steganography.
I said, "Great, great." And I think they
thought that I was going to come in and
give a little three to five minute talk
about steganography, but no, I put
together a 70 slide PowerPoint
presentation about what kind of codes
that al-Qaeda was using and what they
weren't using. And that talk became very
popular. So now we take a quick step to
another project of mine which is after
September 11th. I have a cousin who
works in DC and he had a very close call
that morning on September 11th. Um he
was on his way to give a talk in the
Pentagon and he was running late because
he was having printer problems.
Give me a minute.
Um yeah, because he was having printer
problems and um on his way to the
Pentagon, he was checking his phone and
his phone actually crashed from all of
the messages from people that were
saying, "A plane just hit the Pentagon.
Don't go." Uh so the plane hit right
where he was going to be. And uh some of
the people that he was supposed to brief
were killed. And um so after all of
this, I went out to DC, my first time in
DC and uh to hug my cousin. And then we
went to the memorial at the Pentagon and
we could still smell the smoke and we
put a little American flag out there.
And then we were driving around and my
cousin was saying, "Hey, is there
anything else you'd like to see? This is
your first time in Washington DC." And I
said, "Well, no, you really." And he
said, "Well, thanks. That's nice. I like
seeing you, too. But really, there's
kind of a lot of stuff here to see." And
I said, "You know, I've heard about this
sculpture at CIA headquarters called
Cryptos with a code on it. Um, let's go
see that." And he said, "Okay, that's in
Langley." And we needed to find it. And
CIA is, it doesn't have a street
address. you can't just, you know, pump
it in and and ask the Map Quest or
something. So, um, we found it by
looking at overhead views from Tom
Clansancy movies and stuff. And then we,
um, drove over and we weren't thinking
really clearly at the time. We thought
we were going to just kind of take an
off-ramp and then drive around the
service road, look for the wall and peek
over the wall and see Kryptos. Uh it
didn't work like that because there's no
service road around the CIA. Uh and uh
you take the exit and you're there and
it's a big gate and it's got barbed wire
and a guard shack with a lot of big guys
with guns who were pouring out and
asking you right after se September 11th
very understandable questions, who are
you and why are you here? And you know,
we're like, "Oh, we're here to see uh
Kryptos." And they kind of relaxed a
little and said, "No, sorry. You only
get in with official business only." And
we like, and then my cousin and I, we
kind of looked at each other like, "Can
we talk our way into CIA?" And and we're
saying, "Well, um, you know, can we uh
get an invitation from our Congress
person?" And they said, "No, official
business only." And we're like, "Well,
is there like a family day? could we get
in that way? And the guards were saying,
"No, official business only." And like I
said, these are big guys with guns. And
eventually my cousin and I, we drove
away. And I'm sort of thinking about
this official business. Official
business. And then we come back over to
me talking to the St. Louis FBI and
thinking I was thinking maybe I could
use that as the official business that's
eventually going to get me into CIA
headquarters. And so I put a picture of
Cryptos into one of my slides and every
time I gave the talk, I would say, "Boy,
I'd love to give this talk at CIA
someday. I'd love to give this talk at
CIA someday." And at one point I was
giving the talk at Defcon. This is when
it was at the Alexis Park Hotel in Las
Vegas. And I was like, we were in the
roof, the big roof tent, and I was like,
"Boy, I'd love to give this talk at CIA
someday." And after the talk, people
come up, they give you business cards
and things. And one of them leaned
across the the desk and looked at me in
the eye and said, "I work at Langley. I
think I can get you in." So, I'm like,
"Cool. This is great. We have a CI
analyst that just blew their cover at
Defcon."
And uh we kind of exchanged phone
numbers. They only gave me a first name.
And uh afterwards they said, "Okay, well
can you um send me your slides and we'll
see about getting you in." And I'm like,
"Okay, I I can do that." And uh with the
condition that I can get to see Kryptos
once I'm over there. And they back and
forth. And I said, "And uh but can you
prove to me that you really work at CIA
and you're not just a hacker who's
pulling my chain and saying that you
work at CIA, but you don't really work
at CIA?" And they said, "Well, how am I
supposed to do that?" I said, "Well,
send me an email from an official CIA
email address." And they said, "Well, I
don't have an email from an official CIA
address." And I said, "Well, get an
email from an official CIA address." And
uh some time goes by and I get an email
from DUCIA.gov
which is unclassified cia.gov. And I
wrote back to them. And then they wrote
back to me. So I'm making sure we're
getting back and forth communication.
It's not a spoofed email address. And uh
they invited me out and I got to see
Kryptos up close. And I got to do the
rubbings as you saw uh in one of my
slides there. Um, so that was kind of
cool. Kind of achievement unlocked. I I
got to see Kryptos. Okay. And I did the
rubbings and I brought the rubbings back
home to St. Louis and I made a little
web page visit to CIA. Okay. And I
figured I was done at that point. I'd
gotten to see Kryptos and I had the
rubbings. I had the proof. I wrote it up
and I thought I was done. Well, I wasn't
done. That web page kind of changed my
life because all of a sudden people
started writing to me from all over the
world asking me questions about cryptos
and have you seen this? Did you do that?
And I'm a helpful person so I was trying
to answer their questions. Uh but um it
it just kept going and going. I had an
FAQ and the questions just kept going
and going. Uh, so, um, yeah, the that
web page just went out of control with
people writing to me and then I had the
artist Jim Samborn wrote to me and said,
"Who are you and why do you have a web
page about me?" Cuz he sort of thought I
was sort of stalking him. And I No, no,
no. I I'm fine. I like your work. And uh
so we got kind of in into a a friendly
conversation and I explained that I was
a fan and then I really started getting
more interested in cryptos working on it
and working on different methods and
finding out what had happened which is
that there are four codes on it. Three
of the four been solved, fourth not
solved. Um considered one of the most
famous unsolved codes in the world. And
the first person to publicly solve it
was this guy Jim Gloley in 1999. He's a
California computer scientist. And then
the CIA came forward and said, "Well,
we've got a guy who solved it last year,
1998, one of our analysts who did it on
his own time, David Stein, and he wrote
up kind of a little report and it was
circulated around CIA and that was as
far as it went. And then at the time NSA
came forward and said, "Well, we've got
a team that's done it too, but we're not
going to tell you who and we're not
going to tell you when." Which is very
NSA. The joke around DC is that it
stands for no such agency. So since
then, I've asked more and I found
others. So I know that they put together
a team. I know that two of them at least
were Ken Miller and Denny McDaniels and
that they had done something in 1992 and
they wrote a report and it was sent from
NSA to CIA and
that was it. So let's go forward and
I'll tell you a little bit more. So what
is on cryptos? Well, it's got the four
plates. Two of these plates are what's
called a visionaire table. It's a
hundreds of years old a type of system.
And if you look at it, you can see these
lovely diagonals in it because each
keyed alphabet is shifted over by one.
And so that's a whole half of cryptos.
And then you go to the part that has the
cipher text. And this what's called K1
now part one. And it starts with EM UFP.
And so you take that cipher text, those
two lines, and you apply Visionaire
cipher system with two keywords. The
keywords are cryptos, cryptos, and
palums. Palums is a word for a scroll
that's had stuff scraped off of it, and
then another message written on. So
you've got bits of the old message that
are showing through. And if you use
those two key words, you get the answer,
the plain text answer between subtle
shading and the absence of light lies
the nuance of illusion. So you say, "All
right, she's got to type on her slide."
No, it's that's what the plain text
comes out to be, which is illusion. And
I asked Sambborn
why there's a cue there, illclusions
instead of illusion. And I said, "Was
that a typo on the sculpture?" He said,
"No, it was deliberate, but it's not
what it was that's so important. It's
the orientation or the positioning."
Don't know what that means. So, let's go
on to part two. That starts at line
three and goes to the bottom of the top
plate there. Here's the cipher text of
it. Uh, there was there was a mistake in
this one at the very bottom line of that
uh cipher text. So, I'll I'll go on
here. So this is also visioner with the
two key words cryptos and abscissa.
Absysaa is the word for an xcoordinate
on a graph. And the plain text of this
one says it was totally invisible. How
is that possible? They used the earth's
magnetic field x. The information was
gathered and transmitted underground
to an unknown location. X. Does Langley
know about this? They should. It's
buried out there somewhere. X, who knows
the exact location. Only WW. This was
his last message. X 38° 57 minutes 6.5
seconds north. 77° 8 minutes 44 seconds
west. And then we thought after that it
said ID by Rose. But when he when Sam
Ward said that there had been a mistake
and it was corrected, what it actually
says is X layer 2.
Then there's part three. Starts at the
top of the bottom plate and goes all the
way down to the fourth line from the
bottom. And that one has it's a
different system. It's not a
substitution system like Vaneir. It's a
transposition system. So if you look at
it, you'll see lots of E's and T's and
A's and O's. So all the letters are
there. They're just scrambled in a
particular way. And the plain text for
part three, when you unscramble it,
says, "Slowly, desperately slowly, the
remains of passage debris that
encumbered the lower part of the doorway
was removed. With trembling hands, I
made a tiny breach in the upper left
hand corner. And then widening the hole
a little, I inserted the candle and
peered in. The hot air escaping from the
chamber caused the flame to flicker. But
presently, details of the room within
emerged from the mist. X. Can you see
anything? Q.
Anybody want to guess what that is?
>> I know what it is.
>> This is a paraphrased extract from the
diary of the archaeologist Howard Carter
on November 26th, 1922,
the day that he discovered King Tut's
tomb.
So, a few other interesting things about
uh part three is some of the letters are
a little out of alignment in that top
corner. There's five letters, the d y
ahr. And this is the rubbing that I did.
We don't know exactly what it means.
Sandborn has said that it's important,
but you don't know much beyond that. Um,
and then there's part four at the bottom
bottom four lines there. one of the most
famous unsolved codes in the world
and Sanborn has given clues about part 4
over the years. For example, um in 2010
he told us that the word Berlin is at
that particular location in the plain
text and he's told us that the word
clock appears immediately after it.
Berlin clock. Also in January 2020, he's
told us that the word northeast appears
there. And then the pandemic started and
he kind of wanted to mix things up a
little bit. And so he told us that the
word east appears just before northeast
there. And he that kind of he told one
person in an email and was waiting to
see how long it was going to percolate
into the community. And it took a few
months and then we got it. I called Jim.
Did you just release another clue? Yeah.
Yeah. So we have East, Northeast, and
Berlin Clock.
So the Berlin clocks, Berlin has a lot
of clocks, and we've asked Sambourne
about those clocks a lot. Um, which
clock does he have a favorite clock? And
he says he likes both of them. So we're
like, okay, what are the two most famous
Berlin clocks? and we point out one
clock that has sort of like a a binary
or a base 5 system and uh he says yes,
you should pay attention to that clock.
But finally just last week at a press
event at the spy museum, he announced
another clue and that clue was that
there's only one clock we need to pay
attention to. And this is the I'm not
even going to try and pronounce it, but
it's in a major plaza in Berlin. And it
goes in a circle and it shows all the
different time zones. And it was
something that made a big impression on
Sanborn when he was visiting Berlin in
the late 1980s cuz that was right around
the same time that the Berlin Wall fell.
And so people gathered near that clock
and were protesting and the the wall
felt the wall fell not soon after that.
So, another thing that I found doing my
research is there was a sculpture of his
that was just called the untitled
cryptos piece and he uh sold it to a
private collector and I tracked down a
private collector and it's one of the
dot guys in Los Angeles and I called up
this guy and I said, "Hi, I'm locked." I
tried to make myself sound super
important. Uh, and I said, "Can I come
into your backyard and see the sculpture
that you purchased?" And he said, "Yeah,
sure. Come on over." And I found out
that Sandborn had also made another
version of that that was a little
bigger, about 20% larger, which he'd
given to a museum. But at the
guy's backyard, this is it when I took
pictures when I was there. And it has
two sides. And on one side, it has all
the text of cryptos, but in a different
order. And on the other side it has
Russian text, cerillic text which also
appears on another sculpture of his
which is called the cerillic projector.
And we have cracked the puzzles on both
sides. That's a whole another long talk.
So I'm kind of skipping over this so we
get the jeopardy. So the untitled
cryptos piece as I said there's a
version outside a museum which is the
hershorn museum in Washington DC and we
have it has exactly the same text as is
on the sculpture at the.com guys
backyard it's just slightly different
size and what I discovered when I was
visiting is that there is a difference
in the text which is that there are two
dots that are that appear on that
sculpture, but they don't appear on the
crypto sculpture. Let me see if I got
Yeah, these two dots S.F. dot. So on the
crypto sculpture, it says the exact same
cipher text, which is you have the ZB
SFD, but no dots. And we're not sure
what that means. If they were to appear
on cryptos, um, they would be,
let me get a get my mouse going here.
Come on back here.
>> Can you see my mouse? Okay. And you can
see the red circle. Interesting.
>> It's not showing here. That's where the
dots would be if they were on the crypto
sculpture.
So, uh, also here's another one. The
latitude and longitude. the 38° 57
minutes 6.5 seconds north. Those point
not to Kryptos, but to an area about 150
ft southeast of Kryptos that's still
within that uh yard. So again, I'm
trying to use my mouse here. This white
building with the funny shaped roof,
that is the cafeteria. There is a line
of windows on the left side of the
cafeteria looking out into this
landscaped area. Yeah.
>> You don't have your mouse on screen.
>> You don't?
>> Okay.
>> Oh, just talk. Okay. Uh, white building,
uh, weird looking roof, cafeteria, and
to the left of that is the landscaped
area that Sanborn designed. And the new
headquarters building, which is the
building with the much more interesting
looking roof, uh, is uh, to the left of
that. And then there is a pathway
leading into the new headquarters
building. And Sanborn has designed some
pieces that are on both sides of that
pathway.
Okay, now we're going to try again.
Mouse. There we go. So, cafeteria
Sanborn designed this entire courtyard
and some other pieces over here. Cryptos
itself is about here and the land
longitude and latitude point right
around where my mouse is pointing to
right now. These large stone slabs are
tilted up out of the ground. So sandborn
was trying to replicate geologic forces
that are bringing something out of the
ground that way. And you have large
slabs of granite. And then in between
the slabs of granite, you've got these
uh metal sheets that have Morse code
written on them. And they the Morse code
says things like SOS, shadow forces,
lucid memory, T is your position,
digital interpret. And the reason the
letters are a little cut there is
because the Morse code goes right up
between. So instead of T is your
position, the intent was to say what is
your position and digital
interpretation.
Um
there's probably other words. I've asked
Sam Warren if the Morse code goes all
the way through and he said yes. We have
no idea what it says. Uh, we do know
that after each day that he was working,
the CIA would send people out to scan
everything that he'd done to make sure
he wasn't embedding u bugs or anything
like that in his work. Um, here are some
other pieces. We have a a compass rose
where the needle is not pointing north
and the there is a large stone that is a
load stone. So here the load stone. So
here we have the these three are all of
the same piece at the bottom. So we have
the compass rose which is pointing
towards the load stone and here's
another angle of it the load stone and
some morse code and here's another angle
where you see the slabs are tilted up
and the load stone is right there. And
then there's also another piece that has
no Morse code, no load stone. It's just
kind of there which is odd and maybe
related to other of his work there.
We're not sure.
Uh and then there's the alignment. Uh
many places when you see cryptos you'll
see the picture on the left and Sanborn
was very direct with me. He says don't
show that. That's the wrong side. That's
the ugly side.
Okay. Um how should we do it? And it's
the one on the right. He says yes that
one. That's the front of krypto. So,
take that for uh what it's worth. Um,
let's see. And then we have, as I said,
part four. We don't know what it says.
Famous unsolved code. 97 characters
there. Now, how did Sandborn learn about
codes? Well, he was paired by William
Webster, the director at the time, with
this man named Ed Shite, who was
chairman of a CIA cryptographic center.
and he loved codes. He'd have like ties
with hieroglyphics on them and he taught
Jim Samborn about codes over a period of
a few months and then Sambborn took that
knowledge and encrypted the codes that
he put onto cryptos. So I have met Shite
a few times and pumped him for
information, you know, get him to go to
sushi, buy him drinks, anything I can do
to get information out. Okay? And and he
said things like he did things to mask
the English in part four and he says
that the first three parts we solved it
and we had the benefits of the English
language.
Okay? And you it's like you can look for
most frequent letters and things like
that. But he says that part four you
cannot do that. You cannot solve it by
waiting the English language. And he
also said we solve the first three parts
without recovering the keys first.
So we're not entirely sure what that
means either. We we know that
he's he's implied and he said that
creating a code sometimes you leave it
out there and it's going to be there for
several years and there may be a key for
it but whoever has come in to solve it
they may have forgotten that key. So
there needs to be some sort of a clue
around there as to what the key was or
what the key is. So the first part K1 we
know that the keys were cryptos and
palams and then we had cryptos and
abscissa. So we've put a lot of energy
into thinking what could clue us to the
word of abscissa what could clue us to
the word of palest. We have lots of
guesses but we're really not sure. Um uh
shite has also said he used a little bit
of stego. Stego steganography is a way
of hiding a message in a way that it's
not entirely clear that there was a
message. So we've
the oldest the oldest example of
steganography goes back to the Greek
here historian historian Herodotus
who talked about a king that wanted to
get a message across enemy lines. He
knew that any message he sent, any
messenger he sent would be searched. And
if a message was found, the messenger
would probably be killed, which is a
downside, but a bigger deal is that the
message is not getting where it needs to
go. So what happened then is the king
took a messenger and he shaved the guy's
head,
tattooed a message onto the scalp,
waited for the hair to grow back,
and then sent the messenger across so
many lines. Messenger searched, no
messages found. He gets to uh his
destination, shaves his head, points it
at the uh at the recipient. So this is
not a system that can be used for rapid
messages, but it is a way of hiding a
message.
Um, so what did Ed mean when he said a
little bit of stego? We're not sure. Um,
but he has said that the last part is
English and it uses all the letters.
It's not a case where it just uses like
the first 20 letters or something like
that. So, we know it's 97 letters. So,
Sandborn has been talking a lot about
cryptos over the last few weeks because
of the auction that's going on. And in
an interview with Financial Times,
Financial Times was asking him saying,
"Is there really an answer there?" And
Samborn has said, "Yes, there's really
an answer." And uh yes, he uh was given
a real system by Shite, but he he said
he took Shite's system and then, pardon
my language, he with it.
We don't know what that means. Uh the
the reporter was asking what it mean. I
mean, we do know that this K4 has been
unsolved for what, 35 years now, and a
lot of really smart people have been
working on it, but without success. So,
what the heck did Sanborn do? We know
that he took a real system and that he
messed with it. So, maybe it's not ever
going to be solved by a college educated
cryptologist. Maybe it's going to be
someone who comes out of left field and
has some idea about light and how an
artist might mess with the system. You
fold the paper into origami and fold it.
I I don't know. I don't know. But
Sandborn did something weird to it.
So, um, another piece of information,
the NSA, which is our government agency,
that's one of their missions is solving
codes. So, a lot of very smart people.
In 1992, the CIA's deputy director,
Admiral Stewman,
uh, said to the NSA, he'd worked at the
NSA before, now he's at the CIA. So, he
said to the NSA, "Okay, you guys are so
hot. Let's see how hot you are." and the
Vice Admiral John Mike McConnell who was
at the NSA at the time took up the
challenge and they put together a team.
They put together a team of four people
and they had the uh strength of the
NSA's computers and they ran computer
attacks on the whole thing and they did
solve parts one through three
by December 1992 but could not solve
that fourth part. And then they wrote up
what they did and they sent it on to CIA
and they're done with it. And my group
is very very interested in seeing those
notes by the NSA. And we've gone to the
NSA and said, "Can we see this report?"
And the NSA comes back and says, "No."
And we say, "Well, why not?" And they
say, "Well, it's classified."
Um, and we come back and say, "This is a
recreational cipher that has nothing to
do with national security. Why is it
classified?" And they just, "We can't
tell you it's classified." So, kept on
pushing, kept requesting, and I put
together a formal foyer request, a
Freedom of Information Act request, and
sent it on to the NSA. And I won't go
through all the details, but this was a
multi-year process where I sent
something in and then they came back and
said, "Classified." And I said, "I still
want to see it." And they said, "Are you
willing to pay for copying expenses?"
And I said, "Yeah, sure." And they said,
"Okay, you're first in line." I'm like,
"Great." And then another two years
later, I get, "Okay, you're first in
line." And I'm like, "Whatever. just
just
I have friends who worked in DC and they
said, "Elanka, this is the NSA's way of
saying go away."
Um, but I I kept I kept pushing on it
and finally in May 2013, I got a big
thick envelope that came in the mail,
which is uh all this stuff and at the
top it said, "Please forward to Admiral
Stewman for review." and it had a whole
bunch of stuff redacted on it. Um, but
it was the report and at the bottom,
this is all now on the web now. You can
say approved for release by NSA on May
21st, 2013. Foye case number 61191.
That's me. OKAY.
SO, UM, why hasn't K4 been solved yet?
Well, it's very short. It's just 97
characters. And when you're working on a
code, you generally want a large amount
of cipher text. You can run mathematical
attacks on it. Maybe we have missed
something. Maybe we've been misdirected.
Like maybe when he says that Berlin
clock is in a certain maybe it doesn't
say Berlin clock at that position or
maybe it says Argentina I we don't know.
Um there may be a necessary key that is
only accessible on K4 grounds that you
have to find something in the CIA
museum. And maybe he just messed it up.
Maybe there is some sort of mistake. So,
uh, time goes by and Jim is he gets
email about this all the time and he
finally said he's tired of it and his
health is not the greatest. And he was
convinced by an auction house to put
that last part up for auction, which he
did. And there is an online auction that
is going on right now. Bids are coming
in. I check it every day. And the
auction will end on November 20th. And
this is what the uh auction list was uh
when they first started it. And this is
changed several times, but the basic
part of it was the papers that are going
out with the auction and how there's
going to be a big proof of concept
piece. And I noticed in in here where it
said um Oh, yeah. the bid they're
guesstimating it's going to go for the
same price as what an Enigma machine
would go for. Um, and I noticed this
part where they said uh copies of coding
charts originals at Smithsonian
originals.
>> Yeah. and and cuz I'd looked at the
Smithsonian before it like 20 years ago
and they didn't have anything and now
it's saying hm the original at
Smithsonian and um a couple guys decided
to go make the trip to the Smithsonian
um and this is the page from the
archives of American art and it shows
the Jim Sandborn papers and they wanted
because they listed Jim as one of the
important American artists because he'd
done a lot of art in many different
locations. And so they wanted everything
of his going back to when he was a a
child, literally a child making doodles.
And so they've got a a bit many boxes of
Jim Sandborn stuff. And if you go in and
you look at different box numbers, and
this is what's in box six, and it talks
about different sculptures that he made
and coding charts, and a couple guys
went in, a guy in California asked a
friend of his in DC to go through and
look through these boxes and take
pictures. And the guy took pictures of a
lot of things. And the guy in uh
California was looking through it and he
found one of the pages had a bunch of
little pieces that were all taped to it
and one of those little pieces said
Berlin clock
was and he put and he found other things
and read northeast and he put it all
together. He said this is the answer to
K4. Oh my god. So they sent an email to
Jim Samborn and said, "We think we have
the answer to K4 from Smithsonian." And
Jim got really angry. He was he felt
like they'd stolen it cuz the auction's
going on and this is probably going to
affect the auction. and he told the
auction house and the auction house
contacted these guys and threatened them
with legal action saying if uh they
released this answer it could
potentially lower the price that they'd
get in the auction and so there's a
financial difference there and the guys
weren't really happy about that so they
went to the New York Times about it and
the New York Times published this thing
about a CIA secret and they didn't
publish lish the answer to K4 here. But
the auction house wanted the guys to
sign an NDA, a non-disclosure agreement
with the understanding that they might
get a percentage of what comes in from
the auction if they're able to keep
their mouth shut. And the guys were for
whatever reason were kind of offended by
that. So there's a lot of back and forth
that was going on and is going on. Uh
but um that's kind of where it's at like
right now. So this is from a press event
that Sanborn did at the International
Spy Museum um 4 days ago. I think this
is live stuff going on. And this is the
bid as it was about an hour ago. So,
it's now at $244,000
for the answer into cryptos. With the
next bid, it always has to go up 10%.
Now, they the uh RR auction, the auction
house, they don't do it like eBay where
you have to be there in like the last
minute when it goes live and kind of
really just jam the button to see if uh
you can get the get your uh bid in. They
do it with a 30 minute system so that
anybody who makes a bid, everyone else
has at least 30 minutes in order to
place another bid. So that process is
going to that 30 minute process is going
to start on the 20th which is a few days
from now. So, I am extremely I don't
know. I don't know. I know. I did. I
did. I placed a bid. Um I was bidder
number three. Uh a poultry $12,100
right now. You can see I'm beat by at
least an order of magnitude going in
there. Um this is more than my
retirement account is going.
>> So, I'm just kind of watching it. Now, I
do know a few wealthy people,.com
millionaires. So, I kind of know some of
these people that are bidding. Some I
don't know. There may be some Saudi
prince that just really wants to
know what crypto says and then they'll
put in their bid and find out and then
they'll be not interested in it. What
Jim wants is for whoever wins to then be
what he calls the keeper of it so that
he doesn't keep getting emails all the
time. This other person, the keeper,
will then get these emails all the time.
I have volunteered to be this person. So
>> So they're paying for pain.
>> They're paying for pain. Paying for
pain. Yep. That's what it is. So uh kind
of summarizing here, Cryptos was uh
created around the CIA uh dedicated the
first three parts were solved
independently by various groups. K4 is
still unsolved after 35 years. Um
Sandborg is sick of it. He wants to be
done. He's going to be turning 80 years
old. He wants he has said that the uh
money that comes in is going to be
partially uh given to charity and
partially he's putting it into a fund
for his own medical expenses. Uh
starving artists tend not to have
retirement accounts. So part of that
money is going to go into a fund of his
own and it will all wrap up on the 20th.
Um now about this time I would say hey
I'm selling a book but we're sold out of
books. Sorry. Um, but I do have book
plates. So, anybody that wants an
autographed book plate, these are free.
Uh, these were designed by uh my
co-author and I, Claus and I, and
there's two puzzles hidden on the book
plates. And, um,
that's it.
Okay. Questions? Questions? Um, yes.
>> Okay. Um, so K1, K2, K3, is it visually
obvious that these are separate objects
or if you just walked up to this thing,
would you assume this is one giant
continuous cipher text?
>> Okay, so question was, is it obvious
walking up to it that there are four
codes?
>> Um, no. Uh, half of the sculpture is a
visionary tableau. The other half
there's two plates and within those two
plates you've got four coats. So it's
sort of obvious that one plate could be
something and one plate could be
something else. Um K1 and K2 are on the
top plate. K3 starts at the top of the
bottom plate goes all the way down to
four rows from the bottom. K4 starts
there and finishes out that plate. Uh,
also the untitled cryptos piece, it's
sort of the same, but there it starts
with three, K3, and it goes K3, K4, K1,
K2, K3, K4, and then it like stops
halfway through one of them. They just
kind of went through letters and
stopped.
>> Right. Okay. Um, in the back right
there. Yep. You
>> uh, so can you go back to the page where
at the
Berlin?
Go back to a page where it has what?
>> Clues.
>> Okay, with the clues. With the clues.
Okay, let's see if I can get there.
Um,
no, no,
no. Um, further.
>> Okay, here's K4. But you want you want
the part with the clues? Okay.
>> Yeah, I have a lot of hidden uh hidden
slides.
>> This one. Okay.
>> Okay.
Okay, thank you.
>> Second off, um Okay, so I noticed that I
and I could completely um just like
wrong here, but I notic
I noticed that the K the two A's there,
the K the f the second A is a K.
And the first day is an L. So like you
know and K goes you know is right before
L. So what if you know okay the next
time
>> yeah okay I don't
>> mind.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Ananka.com/cryptos.
Okay. All right. Um yes with the hat.
So, does does the auction include like
>> the plain text and the encryption method
or is there a chance you get the
solution but still not know how we did
it?
>> That's a great question cuz I've often
said like these two guys that have the
answer, they have the answer but they
don't have the method. And until we know
how you go from the cipher text to the
plain text, I don't think it's solved.
So, uh, with the auction, they have
promised that you get not only the
stuff, but you also get an afternoon
with Samborn where he's going to talk
through exactly how everything uh, goes
together. So, it's my uh, big hope that
whoever buys it will have enough in the
way of crypto chops to understand what
he's saying. If not, I'm willing to
volunteer a few people that maybe should
be there with him. uh as as the answer
is being described.
>> All right. Uh
yeah.
>> So do you think that the discovery of
the answer being in the Smithsonian
files was what prompted him to reveal
crypto?
>> It's a great question. Do I think that
the discovery of K4 in the Smithsonian
files has prompted Sanborn to announce
more stuff about K5? Absolutely yes.
Absolutely yes. Now, he'd always hinted
that
even after K4 was solved, there would be
some sort of further mystery to go along
with it because he has said that as an
artist and and he taught art for a
while. That as an artist, one of your
goals is to keep the attention of the
viewer for as long as you can. And a
piece of art that keeps someone's
attention for 10 minutes is a great
thing. And here he has something that's
kept attention for 35 years which he
thinks is fantastic. But at the same
time he's a little embarrassed by it
because artists they tend to have the
two halves of their work. They have part
of their work is the kind that you have
in galleries where people show up and
they drink wine and eat cheese and look
around at what's in the gallery and then
you have the public work which is the
big pieces in the middle of a traffic
circle. Right? And that's how most
artists make their money is from the
public work, but they get their status
from the private work. And here, Kryptos
is a public piece and it's the one that
he's most well known for, which it kind
of sticks in his craw.
Uh, so yeah, say that. All right. Um,
yes. Have you I I know you mentioned
that like when you in your private
conversations you said like the Q
pointed at something like from cryptos I
think it was one there was the Q the
illusion
you mentioned it you said it pointed at
something and then you also mentioned
that there was extra dots when you saw
untitled
>> and I was just wondering like have you
personally spent any time looking at
where Q would be pointing at or maybe
other like trajectories I'm sure it's
maybe on your website I was just
wondering if you commented on that.
>> Okay so let me try and repeat that.
Yeah.
>> So in K1 between subtle shading and the
absence of illusion where illusion is
misspelled with a Q, um, has anyone
played with that? So to have a Q in that
location, the cipher text letter is a K.
And then in the later part where it says
the information was gathered and
transmitted underground where
underground is misspelled with two U's.
Um to get a U to appear in that location
means that the cipher text has an R. So
here we have K R on the sculpture
cryptos. Um we don't know. Maybe there's
more to find there. Maybe that's just
coincidence. We don't know. And I guess
the second part of that was have you
like visually looked at the direction
that those like the R and the K are
pointing at?
>> Have we looked at the direction that
what?
>> Because you mentioned a quote where you
say Sam Warren said Q is pointing at
something.
>> Oh.
>> So have you looked at the visual
location of where those things are
pointing at?
>> Okay. Because it's not what they are,
it's the orientation or the positioning.
Yeah.
>> Um, we've tried we've have several
people who have tried to make 3D models
of the sculpture and look at it at
different times of day and in different
seasons and we don't know.
>> Okay.
Any other questions?
>> Yes. Is there anything or I guess do you
think it's um going to be successful
that whoever buys it will be the keeper
of the
>> do I think that whoever buys it will be
interested in being the keeper of it
maybe um I know uh personally I know two
very wealthy people do millionaires who
are bidding on it and I know One of them
would be interested in being the keeper,
the other one,
>> you know, not so interested. I've told
the other one saying, you know, I'll
happily pay me and I'll happily be the
the keeper uh from there. Uh it is an
interesting thing that if I got that job
and then I would know what the answer
is, um what should I do in terms of my
website and all the things that I'm
doing as the moderator? Well, I would go
to the other two co-odderators and tell
them and we'd have a discussion about
should I continue moderating the list or
should I step back and let them handle
it from there. Um,
yeah,
it we don't know at this point. I just
don't know.
Okay,
>> any other question? Yeah. Do you hope to
come back next year and avail us of all
the new news?
>> Come back next year and have the new
news. Well, I'll probably be coming back
no matter what. Um, AND
I hope I hope I'll have some sort of new
news. Uh, I'll also be talking about my
other project which is 19th century
classified. Had anyone come to my talk
last night?
>> Yeah. Was it good?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. Right. So, I'll probably
have more on that. I'll also be speaking
on that. Okay.
>> All right. Any other questions?
Yeah. No, you're just stretching. Okay.
Okay. Um, you're bidding. You're
bidding. I'll bid you.
Okay. All right. I think that's it then.
Again, thank you.