[Music]
most good spy stories have a secret
message
usually in code
but a master spy can always crack it
today code breaking involves complex
mathematics and relies on powerful
algorithms
but even with
with one coded message no one has been
able to crack
10 feet tall and sitting in plain view
in the backyard of the CIA
correspondent Cohen Chad Cohen
is on the case
[Music]
of all the secrets hidden at the highly
secured CIA headquarters in Langley
Virginia
you may be looking at one of the
strangest meet cryptos it's a copper
monolith inscribed with nearly 2 000
very random looking characters
but there's a message here if you can
break the code and despite countless
attempts since cryptos's 1989
installation that has yet to be done now
you're the Central Intelligence Agency
right you're supposed to be very
intelligent everybody there is
intelligent right you don't have
anything pulled over your eyes well
that's at least what we all like to
believe but with kryptos that's exactly
what Jim Sanborn has done and he is not
the world's most sophisticated
cryptographer in fact Sanborn is not a
cryptographer at all the Mastermind
behind kryptos is an artist
if an unconventional one his workspace
looks more science lab than Art Studio
I work with lodestones
compasses and the Earth's magnetic field
the Coriolis Force these were natural
forces that were invisible those kinds
of things it fascinated me and I set
about to try to make those things
visible for people
when the CIA was looking for a sculpture
to Grace the courtyard of their new
headquarters building
Sanborn wanted to design something that
would stay invisible
a secret code
so how does an artist craft a message
that the best code Breakers in the world
can't crack I set the codes up for him
which means he didn't have to know the
mathematics of it Sanborn found help in
the former chairman of the CIA
cryptographic Center Ed shy who gave Jim
a crash course in cryptography 101
classical cryptography and it's been
defined this way includes substitution
and includes transposition for
substitution take one letter or word and
swap it for another transposition keep
the letters the same just systematically
mix them up pretty straightforward
tricks and yet they've been stumping
would-be code breakers for thousands of
years
Julius Caesar came up with a system
based on substitution to send secret
messages to his generals on the
battlefield it's called the Caesar
Cipher a letter is substituted with
another letter by laying two alphabets
on top of each other and shifting one of
them over a set number of places you get
a whole new alphabet the word film in
this case now becomes ilop complete
gobbley cook if intercepted by an enemy
but if you know how many spaces to shift
the alphabet over it's clear as day
the codes have gotten more complicated
Through the Ages Nazi Germany's Enigma
machine for example which Hitler used
successfully for years before Allied
code Breakers cracked it employed a
mechanical rotor system but ultimately
it just created elaborate substitutions
transposition ciphers have their place
in history too to send secret messages
to his army General Ulysses S Grant
didn't substitute letters he just
carefully mixed them all up Sanborn also
employed this technique in kryptos using
pen and paper so this is the plain text
this is the way it's it's written out in
English by writing the message on a grid
and transposing it to different
positions on a new grid it becomes
unreadable to someone trying to
intercept it and the more times you do
it the more complex it can get so it can
get very complicated very quickly very
quickly complicated maybe to a code
breaker but it's very simple to the
intended recipient if the code is meant
for you you don't have to break it
because when two parties want to
communicate via Cipher they agree ahead
of time on the specific rules of the
system with transquisition you might
agree on how many rows you'd use or how
many times the chart is flipped with
substitution you might agree on how many
spaces to offset the alphabet to make
cryptos Sanborn took both these
techniques used them to encode four
distinct messages
and cut them into copper every letter
was cut out with a jigsaw and took two
and a half years of cutting to do it
cure as the CIA may be
it wasn't long before kryptos went
mainstream through internet message
boards websites hacker conventions
kryptos has become a phenomenon we have
a group of about a thousand people
around the world that are brainstorming
this very very heavily alanka dunnin
whose website has had millions of hits
from would-be crackers is generally
considered to be the leading cryptos
expert in the world even Sanborn says so
but she's only seen the sculpture up
close once well because we can't get in
to see kryptos at CIA because it's at
the center of CIA so alanka took me here
to the hershorn museum in Washington DC
to see a similar Sanborn piece called
antipodes so this is the next best thing
the order of the letters is identical
part one starts here where it says emufp
decrypts to the letters
b-e-t-w-e-e-n between since wind is
resemble anything like the word between
well since Parts 1 2 and 3 of kryptos
were cracked in 1999. it all looks like
pretty much garbage to the untrained eye
and here's the guy who did it La
computer scientist Jim galudely part of
the reason that it's developed a cult
following is that I was able to crack it
and expose it to the world so people are
able to say look some of it really is
solvable it's not just a mass of garbage
letters galue these programs combine
algorithms with rules of thumb for
English grammar and spelling the
computer tries millions of different
character combinations and throws away
the ones that look like nonsense
he's cracked many codes in his life but
he always starts the same way with
what's called a frequency count simply
put he counts he counts up all the
letters in the text and sees how often
each one occurs that works because in
any language certain letters always show
up more often than others whether it's a
cookbook a flight manual or a page from
Hamlet the frequency of each letter will
always stay about the same so in English
on average of all the letters in any
given bit of text E's make up over 12
percent while cues occur much less
frequently less than 0.2 percent
when golugli studied the first two parts
of kryptos he noticed there were just as
many cues as there were E's it was a
tip-off that they were probably standing
in for or substituting for more common
letters
gallugly ran his program on it okay so
you typed this stuff in you typed in
that code and boom this came out this
came out
but as the solution for parts one and
two came out on Jim galugi's screen the
mystery just got deeper twin subtle
shedding and the absence of light lies
the Nuance of Illusion it was totally
invisible how's that possible they used
the Earth's magnetic field the
information was gathered and transmitted
to an unknown location this was his last
message it's another one to scratch your
head yes there's a lot of hmms here
there was nothing to help reveal the
meaning of the sculpture just the
ambiguous words of Jim Sanborn not that
it mattered to the man who actually
cracked it for myself personally I don't
care quite so much about what was being
hidden as to how it was hidden gloogly
quickly discovered that part three of
kryptos was hidden in a radically
different way this one had lots of ease
and only one cue just like it would be
in English I could tell that it was a
transposition cipher because the
frequency of the letters was identical
to the frequency in English remember
what Sanborn was doing in a studio the
transposition he did with that graph
paper
glugly created a computer program that
undid it and eventually he cracked part
three of kryptos as well this section
was recognizable taken right out of
archaeologist Howard Carter's notebook
describing the moment he first opened
King Tut's tomb slowly slowly
desperately slowly the remains of
Passage debris that encumbered the lower
part of the doorway was removed and then
widening the hole of little I inserted
the candle and peered in
the hot air escaping from the chamber
caused the flame to flicker but
presently details of the room within
emerged from the Mist diary excerpts
from famous explorers mysterious
allusions to light and dark even when
sanborn's words are put in the right
order they are cryptic to say the least
between subtle shavings and the Howard
Carter What does it mean well they all
tend to have a common theme of things
hidden things underground things
concealed from sight so that theme may
be something that is going to give us a
clue towards part four
part four is made up of the final 98
letters on the sculpture and only by
breaking that last piece will the true
message of kryptos be revealed but so
far it has proven impervious to all the
techniques of would-be code Breakers
part 4 is hard well number one because
it's very short it's only 97 or 98
characters when cryptanalysts are
working on a code we generally have
large amounts of ciphertext to work with
then you're able to look for the very
subtle mathematical patterns which is
what takes a code apart is it something
really simple that people are missing
No Maybe not maybe maybe not
and he may have had one more trick up
his sleeve something called concealment
it could be a matter of obfuscating the
language before starting to encrypt Ed
sheit has said that he used a little bit
of concealment on part four but we don't
know what that means
it can be concealed in various ways
before ensiphering it to make it even
harder to break the first challenge Stan
is well with masking technique was used
techniques like removing all the vowels
first or spelling the message
phonetically can radically undermine the
code breaking methods foreign
so it may still be a long time before
anyone experiences the thrill of
cracking all of kryptos even Ed who
taught Jim how to make code doesn't know
the solution which makes Jim Sanborn the
only person on Earth who does and he
isn't dropping any hints it wouldn't
help to just kind of get it out I burned
myself
I mean I really like your program but
I'm sorry
[Music]
[Applause]
good
[Music]
[Applause]